Guide to the O'Fallon Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
O'Fallon family papers
1803-1910
WA MSS S-2729
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.05
(4 boxes)
O'Fallon Family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2 (pistol and powder horn): Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Photographs, circa 1845-1910. II. Correspondence, 1810-1841. III. Other Papers, 1803-1903).
Benjamin O'Fallon
Benjamin O'Fallon was born in Kentucky in 1793 to physician James O'Fallon and Frances Eleanor Clark. Following James O'Fallon's death that same year, Frances Clark remarried twice, first to Charles Thruston and then to Dennis Fitzhugh, and had four more children. Benjamin O'Fallon and his older brother John were raised in part by their uncle, the explorer William Clark, in St. Louis. Clark established Benjamin O'Fallon in business as a young man, and in 1817, in his capacity as Governor of the Missouri Territory, appointed O'Fallon "Agent for Indian Affairs for the tribes on the Mississippi above the Oisconsin within the Missouri Territory." In 1819 President James Monroe appointed O'Fallon "Indian Agent on the Missouri." O'Fallon made an expedition to the Yellowstone River in 1825 to treat with tribes at Council Bluffs, and then resigned from his position in early 1827 due to ill health. In 1823 O'Fallon married Sophia Lee (1806-1882); they had six children: Frances O'Fallon Cooper (1830-, married David Middleton Cooper), John O'Fallon (1832-), William O'Fallon (1836-1921), Charles O'Fallon (1838-1912), Emily O'Fallon (1840-1915), and Ellen O'Fallon Smith (1841-1914, married Francis J. Smith). O'Fallon died at his home outside St. Louis in December 1842.
O'Fallon-Smith-Horine Family
Ellen O'Fallon, Benjamin O'Fallon's youngest daughter, married Francis J. Smith (1827-1877) in 1860. Smith was the son of Reuben Smith (1786-1828) and Susan Horine (1805-1835); Susan Horine was the daughter of Jacob Horine and Margaret Madden. Francis J. Smith served as a Lieutenant in Company F, 2nd Regiment Missouri Mounted Infantry in the Mexican War, and later as captain of a cavalry unit in the Confederate army. Ellen and Francis Smith had three children: Albert Sidney Johnston Smith (born 1869), Anita Frances Fitzhugh Smith (born 1872), and John O'Fallon Pope Smith (born 1874). By the 1880s, much of the extended O'Fallon family, including Sophia Lee O'Fallon, Ellen O'Fallon Smith, Emily O'Fallon, William O'Fallon, and Frances O'Fallon Cooper had relocated to San Francisco and San Jose, California.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, photographs, and other papers documenting activities of United States Indian Agent Benjamin O'Fallon and his extended family. Most correspondence consists of letters to Benjamin O'Fallon, concerning Indian affairs in Missouri Territory and throughout what is now the western United States, as well as Missouri politics during the transition from territory to statehood; correspondents include Henry Atkinson, Thomas Hart Benton, William Clark, John C. Calhoun, Henry Leavenworth, John O'Fallon, and Zachary Taylor. The papers also include material relating to O'Fallon's daughter Ellen O'Fallon Smith and her husband Francis J. Smith; Smith's parents, Reuben Smith and Susan Horine Smith; and Susan Horine Smith's father Jacob Horine and grandfather Thomas Madden. The Smith and Horine family papers consist of correspondence and documents including land grants signed by President James Monroe, deeds and other land transactions in Missouri, marriage contracts, estate records, and three bills of sale for slaves purchased by Jacob Horine in 1810 and 1820. The collection includes approximately seventy photographs, including two daguerreotypes but largely dating from the later nineteenth century; these are mostly unidentified portraits of members of the O'Fallon, Smith, Cooper, and Vaughan families of Missouri and California. The papers also include an oil painting by Benjamin O'Fallon's grandson A.D.M. Cooper showing the O'Fallon Mill in Jefferson County, Missouri; and a pistol and powder horn.
African Americans -- Missouri; Frontier and pioneer life -- Missouri; Indian agents; Indians of North America; Land grants -- Missouri; Slave trade -- Missouri; Slavery -- Missouri; Women -- West (U.S.); Missouri River -- Discovery and exploration; Missouri -- Politics and government -- 19th century; Missouri -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; San Jose (Calif.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; United States -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Legal documents -- United States -- 19th century; Oil paintings (visual works) -- United States; Photographs; Pistols; Powder horns; Atkinson, Henry, 1782-1842; Benton, Thomas Hart, 1782-1858; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Clark family; Clark, William, 1770-1838; Cooper, Astley David Middleton, 1856-1924; Fitzhugh, Frances Clark O'Fallon Thruston, 1723-1825; Horine family; Horine, Jacob; Leavenworth, Henry, 1783-1834; Madden, Thomas, 1761-1838; Monroe, James, 1758-1831; O'Fallon, Benjamin; Fallon family; O'Fallon, John, 1791-1865; Smith, Ellen O'Fallon, 1841-1914; Smith, Francis J., 1827-1877; Smith, Reuben, 1786-1828; Smith, Susan Horine, 1805-1834; Taylor, Zachary, 1784-1850
- Photographs, circa 1845-1910s; Series I
  Arrangement
  Series I. is arranged in rough chronological groupings by year or year span.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photographs relating to the extended O'Fallon family.
  - Cased photographs
    - Man with sideburns - quarter plate Daguerreotype, circa 1845 (Box 1)
      Case is broken.
    - A woman - sixth plate Daguerreotype, circa 1845 (Box 1)
      Case is split along spine.
    - A woman, her jewelry highlighted in gold - quarter plate tintype, circa 1860s (Box 1)
  - Loose photographs, 1860s-1910s
    Arranged in rough chronological groupings by year or year span.
    - Men and boys, St. Louis - cartes de visite, circa 1860s (Box 1)
      Contains fourteen cartes de visite photographs of various individuals. All are taken by St. Louis, Missouri photographers. Few sitters are identified, though, one is labelled as belonging to the Freimont family.
    - Women and girls, St. Louis - mostly cartes de visite, circa 1860s-1880s (Box 1)
      Contains twenty-four photographs, mostly cartes de visite, of various individuals. All are taken by St. Louis, Missouri photographers. Few sitters are identified, though, a few are labelled as belonging to the Cooper, Duke and Farmer families.
    - Men and women, various locales - mostly cartes de visite, circa 1860s-1910s (Box 1)
      Contains twenty-one photographs, mostly cartes de visite, of various individuals. Few sitters are identified, though, a few are labelled as belonging to the Vaughan family. The folder also includes two post cards of The Cedars in Barnhart, Missouri, circa 1910s.
    - Various individuals, California - cabinet cards, 1870s-1880s, 1910s (Box 1)
      Contains eleven photographs, mostly cabinet cards, of various individuals taken by California photographers. Some cabinet cards are labeled, and belong to the O'Fallon, Smith and Patton families. The folder also includes one post card, circa 1910s, of the home of Dr. A.S.J. Smith, located at what is now 250 South 14th Street, San Jose, California.
- Correspondence, 1810-1841; Series II
  Series II. is arranged in rough chronological groupings by year or year span.
  This series consists of correspondence relating to Benjamin O'Fallon, his family, and his service as a military officer and Indian Agent.
  - O'Fallon, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - Louisville, Kentucky, 1814 June 28 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John O'Fallon to his brother Benjamin O'Fallon, introducing an acquaintance and asking that he be introduced in turn to their uncle William Clark.
  - Fitzhugh, Fanny to Benjamin O'Fallon - Louisville, Kentucky, 1816 August 3 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed, from Fanny Fitzhugh to her son Benjamin O'Fallon, transmitting in a letter to her from John O'Fallon regarding a posting to Green Bay, Wisconsin.
  - O'Fallon, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - Rapids Fox River, 1816 August 24 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John O'Fallon to his younger brother Benjamin O'Fallon, giving advice on the latter's desire to enter the Indian trade.
  - Clark, William to Benjamin O'Fallon - St. Louis, Missouri, 1817 May 25 (Box 1)
    Manuscript document, signed by William Clark, Governor of Missouri Territory, appointing his nephew Benjamin O'Fallon as Indian Agent for Missouri.
  - O'Fallon, John to Benjamin O'Fallon, 1817-1836 (Box 1)
    Seven autograph letters, signed by John O'Fallon, to his brother Benjamin O'Fallon. Accompanied by carte de visite photograph of John O'Fallon.
  - Taylor, Zachary to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Howard, Green Bay, Wisconsin, 1818 June 2 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Zachary Taylor, future President of the United States, then in command of Fort Howard in what was the Michigan Territory, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding Indian policy, mutual acquaintences, politics, allusions to dueling, and other matters.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart to Thomas Claiborne and William G. Blount - St. Louis, Missouri, 1818 December 15 (Box 1)
    Two autograph letters, signed by Thomas Hart Benton, a St. Louis lawyer and future U.S. Senator, to Tennessee Representatives Thomas Claiborne and William G. Blount, introducing Benjamin O'Fallon, with reference to impending Missouri statehood.
  - Calhoun, John C. to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington D.C., 1819 March 8 (Box 1)
    Manuscript letter, signed by John C. Calhoun to Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding Benjamin O'Fallon's appointment to the Indian Agency.
  - Clark, William to Benjamin O'Fallon, 1819 May 21 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by William Clark, Governor of Missouri Territory, to his nephew Benjamin O'Fallon, serving as Indian Agent.
  - Calhoun, John C. to Benjamin O'Fallon - various letters, 1819-1822 (Box 1)
    Contains four manuscript letters, signed by John C. Calhoun, then Secretary of War, to Benjamin O'Fallon, who was the Indian Agent for Missouri. The letters are dated: 18 August 1819, 12 July 1820, 22 May 1821 and 29 May 1822.
  - Calhoun, John C. to Benjamin O'Fallon - various letters, 1819-1824 (Box 1)
    Contains manuscript copies of letters by John C. Calhoun, then Secretary of War, to Benjamin O'Fallon, who was the Indian Agent for Missouri. The letters are dated: 18 August 1819, 18 March 1822, 1 June 1824 and 14 June 1824.
  - Gantt, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - Camp Missouri, 1820 March 1 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John Gantt to Major Benjamin O'Fallon, declining an invitation to a buffalo hunt, due to health reasons.
  - Green, Duff to Benjamin O'Fallon - Canton, Missouri, 1820 April 22 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Duff Green to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding his fear of predatory Indian tribes.
  - Atkinson, Henry to Winfield Scott - St. Louis, Missouri, 1821 October 19 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by General Henry Atkinson, to General Winfield Scott, introducing Benjamin O'Fallon.
  - Calhoun, John C. to Benjamin O'Fallon - various letters, and invitations, circa 1821-1826 (Box 1)
    Contains two autograph letters signed by John C. Calhoun, then U.S. Vice President, to Benjamin O'Fallon, who was the Indian Agent for Missouri. The letters are dated 10 June 1825 and 8 February 1826. Also included are two engraved invitations from Mrs. Calhoun, filled out to Benjamin O'Fallon (circa 1821), and an autograph note expressing Mrs. Calhoun's regret at not being able to receive guests due to the death of Governor Charles Pickney (circa 1824).
  - O'Fallon, Benjamin to John C. Calhoun - Washington, D.C., 1822 January 1 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Benjamin O'Fallon to John C. Calhoun, regarding gifts for the Indians, with a list of proposed gifts.
  - McKenney, Thomas L to John C. Calhoun - Washington, D.C., 1822 January 5 (Box 1)
    Manuscript letter, signed by Thomas L. McKenney to then Secretary of War, John C. Calhoun.
  - Atkinson, Henry to John C. Calhoun - St. Louis, Missouri, 1822 February 22 (Box 1)
    Manuscript copy of a letter from General Henry Atkinson to John C. Calhoun, regarding William Ashley and Andrew Henry.
  - Benton, Thomas H. to Benjamin O'Fallon - various letters, 1822-1844 (Box 1)
    Contains seven autograph letters signed by Senator Thomas Hart Benton to sometimes Indian Agent Benjamin O'Fallon. The letters discuss political matters, Indian affairs and other topics. Also includes a carte de visite photograph of Thomas Hart Benton.
  - Leavenworth, Henry to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atkinson, Nebraska, 1823 October 31 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Colonel Henry Leavenworth, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding loaning guns to fur trader Jean Pierre Cabanné, and other matters.
  - Leavenworth, Henry to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atkinson, Nebraska, 1823 December 30 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Colonel Henry Leavenworth, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding soldiers hunting on Indian lands.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington, D.C., 1824 April 6 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Thomas Hart Benton, to Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding the Indian Bill and machinations of Senator David Barton against O'Fallon and his uncle William Clark.
  - Gale, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atkinson, Nebraska, 1824 July 18 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John Gale, an army surgeon at Fort Atkinson, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding the military expedition against the Arikara Indians in 1823.
  - Ketchum, Daniel to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atkinson, Nebraska, 1824 July 18 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Major Daniel Ketchum, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, in response to questions about the Arikara Expedition of 1823.
  - Riley, Bennett C. to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atkinson, Nebraska, 1824 July 18 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by Captain Bennett C. Riley, to Indian Agent Benjamin O'Fallon, in response to questions about the Arikara Expedition of 1823.
  - Leavenworth, Henry to Benjamin O'Fallon - Fort Atikinson, Nebraska, 1824 (Box 1)
    Two autograph letters, signed by Colonel Henry Leavenworth, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, pertaining to tensions between them, with a veiled threat of a duel. The Dates are17 July 1824 and 23 July 1824. Also included is a letter of introduction from Henry Leavenworth for Indian Agent J. Daugherty, dated 13 April 1824.
  - Scott, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington, D.C., 1825 January 1 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John Scott, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, describing events in Washington, etc.
  - O'Fallon, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - St. Louis, Missouri, 1825 April 2 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John O'Fallon, to his brother Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding politics and government appointments. Also contains an unidentified carte de visite photograph of a man, taken by J. Sydney Brown, a St. Louis, Missouri photographer.
  - Conant, Samuel L. to Benjamin O'Fallon - New York, 1825 May 12 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter by Samuel L. Conant to Benjamin O'Fallon, seeking examples of "Indian Eloquence" on a lettersheet with printed text detailing his quests for said eloquence.
  - O'Fallon, John to Benjamin O'Fallon - St. Louis, Missouri, 1825 October 1 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John O'Fallon, to his brother Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding troubles with Indians. Also contains an unidentified carte de visite photograph of a man, taken by J. Sydney Brown, a St. Louis, Missouri photographer.
  - Invitation to Benjamin O'Fallon - St. Louis, Missouri, 1825 October 24 (Box 1)
    Autograph invitation to Benjamin O'Fallon and others to a dinner in St. Louis, Missouri following their return from the Yellowstone River.
  - Sanford, John F.A. to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington, D.C., 1828 January 30 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by John F.A. Sanford, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, describing events in Washington, etc.
  - Edwards, Ninian to Benjamin O'Fallon - Bellevue, Illinois, circa 1828 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter by Ninian Edwards, Governor of Illinois, to Benjamin O'Fallon, Indian Agent, regarding lawsuits against him by citizens of Missouri.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington D.C., [1829] December 9 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter by Thomas Hart Benton to Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding the removal of Indians west of the Mississippi River.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart to Benjamin O'Fallon - Washington D.C., 1830 January 19 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter by Thomas Hart Benton to Benjamin O'Fallon, regarding Indian Agent John F. Hamtramck and his corruption.
  - Green, Duff to Benjamin O'Fallon - printed circular, circa 1832 (Box 1)
    Printed circular presenting A. Harry (?) as an agent of Duff Green's newspaper United States Telegraph. The circular also contains information regarding Duff Green's break with the administration of Andrew Jackson over the latter's dismissal of John C. Calhoun as Vice President.
  - O'Fallon, Benjamin - petition and letter to John O'Fallon - Fayette, Missouri and Indian Retreat, 1835 (Box 1)
    Manuscript petition to John O'Fallon, signed by 10 supplicants, requesting that he ask his brother, Benjamin O'Fallon, to run for Governor of Missouri, dated November 13, 1835. Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed by Benjamin O'Fallon to his brother John O'Fallon, dated December 29, 1835, declining the honor.
  - Mitchell, David Dawson to Benjamin O'Fallon - St. Louis, Missouri, 1841 June 18 (Box 1)
    Autograph letter, signed by David Dawson Mitchell, to Benjamin O'Fallon, requesting his support in his application for Superintendent of Indian Affairs.
- Other papers, 1803-1903; Series III
  Series III. is arranged in rough chronological groupings by year or year span.
  This series consists of correspondence and other material relating to Benjamin O'Fallon, as well as the extended O'Fallon family.
  - Smith, Reuben - manuscripts, 1803-1828 (Box 1)
    Deeds, letters, accounts, marriage contract, estate records, and other material belonging to or relating to Reuben Smith of Missouri. Includes two land grants signed by James Monroe.
  - Two surveys, and one deed for land in Louisiana (Missouri Territory), 1804-1825 (Box 1)
    Manuscript survey and description by Antony Soulard of land belonging to Jacob Horine in Alta Louisiana, in Spanish, 1804. Manuscript deed for land belonging to Gabriel Cerre, in French, signed by Marie Philippe Leduc, with paper seal, 1805. Manuscript survey of "Township No. 39, North, Range and East," showing land belonging to Pierre Chouteau and Thomas Madden, circa 1825.
  - O'Fallon Family - manuscripts, 1808-1885 (Box 1)
    Letters, documents and other material relating to the extended O'Fallon and Smith families of Missouri. Includes document signed by Sheriff J. Henry Dodge regarding the forced sale of land and property of Ezekial Able to John Smith T (brother of Reuben Smith) and Thomas Oliver, 1808; autograph letter, signed, from J. Cabell Breckenridge to William J. Lewis, 1819; three autograph letters, signed, from Ann C. Thruston to Benjamin O'Fallon, 1816-1820; autograph letter, signed, from D. Fitzhugh to John O'Fallon, 1821; autograph letter, signed, from Benjamin O'Fallon to Col. William Anderson, 1822; autograph letter, signed, from John Croghan to John O'Fallon, 1843; autograph letter, signed, from Will. C. Carr to Benjamin O'Fallon, 1837; autograph letter, signed, from D. M. Cooper to John O'Fallon, 1849; autograph letter, signed, from P.O. Lee to J.C. Palmer.
  - Horine, Jacob - three bills of sale for slaves, circa 1810-1820 (Box 1)
    Contains three bills of sale for slaves bought by Jacob Horine within Missouri. Listed are the assets in Jacob Horine's estate, including his slaves. The bills of sale are dated 21 July 1810, 3 November 1810, and 25 Oct 1820.
  - Horine-Madden family - manuscripts, 1817-1844 (Box 1)
    Accounts, receipts, estate records and other material relating to the Horrine-Madden family of early Missouri.
  - Document appointing Benjamin O'Fallon as Indian Agent on the Missouri, 1819 March 3 (Box 3 (Oversize))
    Framed document, signed by President James Monroe and Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams.
  - Smith, Francis J. - manuscript and printed material, 1838-1887 (Box 1)
    Material relating to the land transactions, lawsuits, financial matters and other affairs of Francis J. Smith.
  - Cardinal Vaughan - newspapers and photographs, 1880s-1903 (Box 1)
  - O'Fallon Mill, Jefferson Co., Missouri, 1881; 22.5 x 17 cm. (Box 4 (Oversize))
    Oil painting by Astley David Middleton Cooper, framed. Titled and signed on verso, "O'Fallon Mill, Jefferson Co., A.D. Cooper, 1881."
  - Handwritten genealogy of Frances Clark, mother of Benjamin O'Fallon (Box 1)
    Ink and pencil, most likely from the late 19th or early 20th century.
  - Powder horn, with metal base, circa 1830; 2 (Box 2 (Art))
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
    From the family of Benjamin O'Fallon. Made from cowhorn, the powder horn is 15 inches from base to tip. It lacks the plug.
  - Flintlock pistol - Tennessee Kentucky type, circa 1810-1830 (Box 2 (Art))
    .36 caliber, 8.5" octagonal rifled barrel with iron trigger-guard, and tiger maple full stock; the lock is marked Bird Brothers, Philadelphia. O'Fallon family tradition was that this was a dueling pistol, but that cannot be verified; it may be an officer's sidearm. Descended in the Benjamin O'Fallon family.